const e=JSON.parse(`[{"title":"PAPER A RECALL JUNE 2016"},{"number":1,"question":"Mrs Davis is a 55-year-old woman who has been taken to A&E by her daughter. She was found to be behaving increasingly oddly over the past few days, isolating herself, suspicious of the neighbours, preoccupied with ideas that she is being persecuted. Further investigation reveals that, following a recent Deep Vein thrombosis, the GP had abruptly stopped one of her usual prescribed medications. Which one of the following prescribed medications is most likely to be implicated in the above scenario?","options":{"A":"Testosterone","B":"Androgen","C":"Estrogen","D":"Progesterone","E":"Thyroxine"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Hormone Replacement Therapy is frequently given to post-menopausal women. Estrogen is a powerful psychoactive hormone, with widespread physiological effects. There are reports indicating that sudden withdrawal of estrogens has precipitated mood disturbances and psychosis-like presentations."},{"number":2,"question":"Ms. Triggs has a diagnosis of Bipolar Affective Disorder Type II, with two previous hypomanic episodes and numerous depressive episodes. Her mood is currently low, and she is experiencing insomnia, increased appetite, and negative ruminations. You are considering starting an antidepressant. Which of these is least likely to precipitate a manic switch?","options":{"A":"Fluoxetine","B":"Sertraline","C":"Bupropion","D":"Amitryptiline","E":"Venlafaxine"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Tricyclics like Amitryptiline and Venlafaxine in particular carry a greater risk of precipitating a switch into mania. SSRIs have also been implicated; there is some evidence for bupropion also contributing to manic switch, but this evidence is less robust than for the other agents listed."},{"number":3,"question":"Jack Lyndon is a 43-year-old man with a long history of depression, who one month previously had been started on an antidepressant he's not previously tried. He has found some alleviation in his depressive feelings, his hypersomnia and lethargy. He is invited to a dinner party and part-way through the evening he begins to feel unwell, with facial flushing. The host offers to measure Mr. Lyndon's blood pressure with a portable machine, and it is found to be 208/106. Which of the following is most likely to be related to the hypertensive crisis?","options":{"A":"Tranylcypromine","B":"Fluoxetine","C":"Mirtazapine","D":"Sertraline","E":"Agomelatine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"When MAOIs such as Tranylcypromine are taken, the patient must be warned to avoid foods (such as mature cheese and red wine) containing tyramine (a monoamine precursor), as it can precipitate a hypertensive crisis, which is potentially life-threatening."},{"number":4,"question":"William and Diane Corndale are seeking help for infertility. It is 5 years since they have been trying to conceive, but have so far been unsuccessful. Which of the following is the most likely consequence of this stressor?","options":{"A":"Negative impact on self-esteem","B":"Decrease in frequency of sexual intercourse","C":"Increase in number of disagreements","D":"Feelings of guilt","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Difficulty in conceiving may place significant stress on a couple, and there's the potential for a wide spectrum of psychological struggles to ensue."},{"number":5,"question":"Your colleague Bill asks you to call a GP practice on his behalf. He reads out loud the number for you, and you manage to remember it long enough to dial it. What kind of memory does this illustrate?","options":{"A":"Semantic memory","B":"Working memory","C":"Implicit memory","D":"Episodic memory","E":"Declarative memory"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Working memory is the ability to process and remember information at the same time, and usually hold small amounts of information (typically around 7 items)."},{"number":6,"question":"Mrs Molloy has been struggling with feelings of depression and self-blame. She's been talking about her childhood experiences in psychotherapy and described the way her father would make her follow very strict rules. On one occasion, she returned home only a few minutes after her curfew, and she was beaten by him with a belt. The parenting style she is describing is known as","options":{"A":"Permissive","B":"Indulgent","C":"Neglectful","D":"Authoritarian","E":"Secure"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Authoritarian parenting tends to be restrictive and rule-focused. It is designed to teach the child to be submissive and fearful, to cope with a harsh world."},{"number":7,"question":"Mr Cox is a 56-year-old man with chronic schizophrenia, who has been smoking 20 cigarettes a day since his teenage years. On a routine medical examination, it is noted that the BP in his right arm is 184/98, and on the left 155/80. The examination is repeated on several other occasions, and the difference in blood pressure between the arms is found to be consistent. Which artery is most likely to be affected?","options":{"A":"Subclavian artery","B":"Middle cerebral artery","C":"Posterior inferior cerebral artery","D":"Cerebellar artery","E":"Radial artery"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The vignette suggests that the subclavian artery is affected, most likely by atherosclerosis. Discrepancy in left and right arm blood pressures is associated with higher risk of cardiovascular events."},{"number":8,"question":"Mrs Dellmore, who is 83 years old, has been referred to a clinic for older adults following concerns that she has been forgetting the names of common objects, and losing her way on returning from the local shops. The psychologist uses a number of rating measures. Which one is observer-rated?","options":{"A":"PHQ-9","B":"GAD-7","C":"NPI-C","D":"SADQ","E":"Meyers Briggs"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The Neuropsychiatric Inventory-Clinician rating scale is observer-rated, focusing on neuropsychiatric symptoms in people with dementia. The other scales are self-rated."},{"number":9,"question":"Brian Hughes is a war veteran who has been diagnosed with PTSD. He reports that his sleep is particularly disrupted and undergoes investigation at a sleep clinic. Which of the following findings is most consistent with sleep and PTSD?","options":{"A":"Increased frequency of rapid eye movements in REM sleep","B":"Longer duration of stage 2 NREM sleep","C":"Longer total sleep time","D":"Decreased sleep onset latency","E":"Decreased stage 1 NREM sleep"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The effect on sleep in people with PTSD is the focus of much research and there have been several findings; the most consistent is that in those with PTSD (compared with controls), there is an increase in average number of rapid eye movements per minute in REM sleep."},{"number":10,"question":"Mr. Welton's memory is being tested. He has been given a list of items to study. Once he has finished studying the items he is given another list of items to study, before being asked to recall as many items as he can from the first list, in any order. What memory test does this allude to?","options":{"A":"Semantic Memory","B":"Immediate Free Recall","C":"Delayed Free Recall","D":"Iconic Memory","E":"Working Memory"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"This test includes a delay prior to the free recall of items on the first list; hence it is 'delayed' free recall."},{"number":11,"question":"Timmy has a pet mouse which he spends time with. As part of a psychological experiment, his father creates a loud noise whenever Timmy is playing with his mouse, and the noise frightens Timmy. This is done a number of times, so that whenever Timmy sees his pet mouse, he feels frightened. Which of these is now classed as the conditioned stimulus?","options":{"A":"The mouse","B":"The noise","C":"The mouse + noise","D":"The fear","E":"The fear + noise"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The mouse was previously a neutral stimulus; it has been associated with an unconditioned stimulus (the noise) that naturally triggers an automatic response in Timmy (fear). The mouse therefore becomes a conditioned stimulus, eliciting fear in Timmy."},{"number":12,"question":"You are about to go to A&E to assess a patient who is feeling suicidal. Which demographic description has got the strongest association with completed suicide?","options":{"A":"Elderly male","B":"Elderly female","C":"Young female","D":"Middle-aged male","E":"Widow"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Rates of suicide in men is nearly four times higher than that of women, with middle-aged men at highest risk."},{"number":13,"question":"Mr Loughton has come to see you in clinic, following a referral from the Police. You are aware that your colleague will want to know what his future risk of sexual violence will be. Which of the following is the strongest predictive factor for future sexual violence?","options":{"A":"History of alcohol misuse","B":"History of depression","C":"Having numerous siblings","D":"History of past sexual violence","E":"History of bipolar affective disorder"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"History of past sexual violence is the strongest predictor for future sexual violence."},{"number":14,"question":"Mrs Swami is about to start taking Olanzapine for a newly diagnosed psychotic illness. Her nephew is reading up on Olanzapine's metabolism and modes of action. What property of a drug such as Olanzapine aids its movement into fat tissues?","options":{"A":"It induces Cytochrome CYP450","B":"It is lipophilic","C":"It is metabolized in phase I oxidative metabolism","D":"It is highly protein-bound","E":"It is renally excreted"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Lipophilic molecules travel well across the phospholipid bilayer of the cell membrane. Greater the lipophilicity, higher the movement of drugs into fat tissues."},{"number":15,"question":"Angela Stubbs has been participating in psychotherapy for the past seven months. She has the sense that the process has been helping her develop a more robust sense of self, a feeling of continuity, and of affiliation with others. What term best describes this process?","options":{"A":"Identity formation","B":"Identity foreclosure","C":"Identity moratorium","D":"Identity diffusion","E":"Identity fusion"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Identity formation or individuation is a process in which the sense of self becomes more distinct; this can be accompanied by an increased ability to engage with others."},{"number":16,"question":"Sammy Taylor is coming to see you in clinic as an emergency book-in. He is 19 years old and has developed some voice-hearing experiences and bizarre thoughts regarding the MI5. Which of these might be a precipitating factor?","options":{"A":"Having been adopted at the age of 7 months","B":"Having a brother who has a diagnosis of schizophrenia","C":"Having lost his adoptive father to a road traffic accident two weeks previously","D":"Having had a traumatic birth","E":"Having dropped out of school prematurely at the age of 15"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The others may be contributing factors, but most are predisposing rather than precipitating. A precipitating factor has a strong temporal link to the onset of the episode of mental illness."},{"number":17,"question":"Thomas Wilkins is a 56-year-old man who presented to his GP with some personality changes, including anxiety, depression, confusion and memory loss. His movements lacked coordination and he began to experience falls. There was a suspicion of vCJD and a head MRI was arranged. Which of the following signs gives an accurate diagnostic sign for vCJD (variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease)?","options":{"A":"Hypothalamus hyperintensity","B":"Pulvinar sign","C":"Frontal lobe atrophy","D":"Cerebellar hypointensity","E":"Pineal gland sign"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The Pulvinar sign (symmetrical hyperintensity in the pulvinar nuclei of the thalamus) on brain MR images is a highly accurate sign for vCJD."},{"number":18,"question":"Andrew is a 10-day-old genetic male who appears not to have developed the characteristic of male genitalia as expected. Biochemical tests are performed. The cause is also linked to excessive virilisation in female adults. Which condition does this relate to?","options":{"A":"17-beta-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase deficiency","B":"17-alpha-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase deficiency","C":"5-alpha-reductase deficiency","D":"5-beta-reductase deficiency","E":"3-beta-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"17-beta-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase deficiency is an autosomal recessive form of male pseudohermaphroditism due to impaired testicular conversion of androstenedione to testosterone, affecting male sexual development."},{"number":19,"question":"Michael Stills is 32 years old and has developed depression for the first time in his life. You meet him and take a history. Which of the following is a precipitating factor for his depression?","options":{"A":"Being married for the past 2 years","B":"The loss of his baby son from cot death at the age of 4 months","C":"Growing up in a large city","D":"Working as a teaching assistant","E":"Having a parent who has a diagnosis of chronic anxiety disorder"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Bereavement is strongly associated with the onset of depression."},{"number":20,"question":"Mrs Mokolo has been reading up on the biochemistry of SSRIs, after you started her on Sertraline for an episode of depression. She reminds you that the serotonergic receptor with auto-regulatory function in synaptosomes (5-HT terminals) is:","options":{"A":"5-HT1A","B":"5-HT1B","C":"5-HT2A","D":"5-HT2B","E":"5-HT1D"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"5-HT1B auto-receptors are located in serotonin terminals. They regulate 5-HT reuptake, as well as modulating 5-HT release and synthesis."},{"number":21,"question":"Which of the following statements about dopamine D2 receptors is NOT true?","options":{"A":"They affect adenylyl cyclase activity","B":"They are excitatory","C":"They act via the tuberoinfundibular pathway","D":"They constitute both pre and post-synaptic receptors","E":"They are G protein-coupled"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"D2 receptors are inhibitory receptors that have both pre- and post-synaptic functions. They inhibit adenylyl cyclase activity and act via the tuberoinfundibular pathways that inhibit prolactin."},{"number":22,"question":"Homosexuality is no longer considered as a mental disorder. Which edition of the International Classification of Diseases (ICD) saw the removal of homosexuality as a mental illness?","options":{"A":"ICD 1","B":"ICD 2","C":"ICD 3","D":"ICD 9","E":"ICD 10"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The World Health Organisation's ICD-9, published in 1977, listed homosexuality as a mental illness. It was later removed from the ICD-10."},{"number":23,"question":"George Smith, a 74-year-old retired teacher, presents to your outpatient clinic with his wife, Mary. She has expressed her concern that George has been spending an increasing amount of time in the betting office. His medical history includes hypertension, Parkinson's disease, depression and gastrooesophageal reflux disease. Of the following medications he is taking, which is the most likely cause of pathological gambling?","options":{"A":"Zopiclone","B":"Levodopa","C":"Omeprazole","D":"Metoprolol","E":"Mirtazapine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Impulsive and compulsive behaviour is a possible side effect of some medications used to treat Parkinson's disease, including levodopa."},{"number":24,"question":"Which of the following medications acts on NMDA receptors?","options":{"A":"Memantine","B":"Mirtazapine","C":"Methadone","D":"Tranylcypromine","E":"Moclobemide"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Antidementia medication, Memantine, works by blocking N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) glutamate receptors."},{"number":25,"question":"You are asked by the matron in A&E to review Sarah Moore, a 43-year-old mother of two, who separated from her husband, John, earlier this year. For the past few months, Sarah has been spreading lies about John to other parents, including mistruths that he is taking their two children out of school during school hours. This resulted in a meeting between John and the school welfare officer. Sarah appears happy at this conclusion and tells you that it proves she is the better parent. These false accounts appear to coincide with John's new relationship. What is the name given to this particular phenomenon?","options":{"A":"Confabulation","B":"Falsification","C":"Pseudologia fantastica","D":"Déjà vu","E":"Depersonalisation"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Pseudologia fantastica is the production of convincing false accounts often with apparent sincere conviction. It is a feature of Munchausen's disease."},{"number":26,"question":"In a strange situation experiment, Bobby, a 2-year-old boy, is only comforted when his mother returns to the room and is not comforted by the stranger. What type of attachment is seen here?","options":{"A":"Secure attachment","B":"Anxious Avoidant","C":"Anxious Resistant","D":"Disorganized","E":"Insecure"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Secure attachment: Ainsworth constructed a strange situation experiment with 2 separation and 2 reunion episodes. The most common type of attachment behaviour in the Western world is secure."},{"number":27,"question":"Mollie, a five-year-old girl, plays with her doll and talks to it as though it is real. What is the name of this phenomenon?","options":{"A":"Artificialism","B":"Symbolic play","C":"Egocentrism","D":"Animism","E":"Centration"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Animism is the belief that plants, inanimate objects, and natural phenomena possess a living soul and have human feelings and intentions."},{"number":28,"question":"Mandip is a 33-year-old Sikh male from India. He is an IT contractor and speaks English at work. He regularly goes to the pub after work for drinks with his colleagues. When he goes home he speaks Punjabi with his parents and wears traditional robes. What form of acculturation does Mandip display?","options":{"A":"Marginalisation","B":"Assimilation","C":"Integration","D":"Separation","E":"Division"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Integration refers to both high retention of one's own cultural values and high adoption of the practices of the new culture."},{"number":29,"question":"You are discussing clozapine treatment with Luke, a 24-year-old male with treatment refractory paranoid schizophrenia. Which of the following lifestyle factors will produce an increased level of clozapine?","options":{"A":"He plans to stop smoking by his next birthday in two months' time","B":"He doesn't drink coffee or tea","C":"He stopped taking fluvoxamine six years ago following a single episode of depression.","D":"He drinks on average four pints of lager every week","E":"He is taking propranolol for anxiety"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Clozapine plasma concentrations can rise 1.5 times in the 2-4 weeks following smoking cessation and in some instances by 50-70% within 2-4 days."},{"number":30,"question":"Which of the following is an aspect of pharmacokinetics?","options":{"A":"Neurotransmitter synthesis","B":"Neurotransmitter storage","C":"Storage release","D":"Reuptake","E":"Absorption"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Pharmacokinetics is concerned with the time course and disposition of drugs in the body (what the body does to the drug). It involves the processes of Absorption, Distribution, Metabolism and Elimination (ADME)."},{"number":31,"question":"In his 1987 book, Le Suicide, what did sociologist Emile Durkheim conclude?","options":{"A":"Suicide could be attributed to a lack of social capital","B":"Suicide rates are higher in women than in men","C":"Suicide was more common during times of war","D":"Suicide was more common in civilians than in soldiers","E":"The risk of suicide is fixed"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Durkheim noticed that suicide rates were higher among Protestants (where integration levels were low) than Catholics and Jews (where integration is normal), arguing that stronger social control among Catholics resulted in lower suicide rates."},{"number":32,"question":"Shalinee, a 30-year-old florist, has a history of epilepsy for which she takes carbamazepine. She is planning to start a family with her husband, David and seeks your advice on medication during pregnancy. Which of the following pharmacokinetic changes occurs during pregnancy?","options":{"A":"Reduced volume of distribution","B":"Increased plasma protein binding","C":"Reduced absorption from intramuscular site of injection","D":"Increased renal elimination","E":"Reduced rate of metabolism"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Renal blood flow is increased by 60-80% during pregnancy, and glomerular filtration rate rises by 50%, leading to enhanced elimination of drugs."},{"number":33,"question":"During a cognitive examination, Betty, an 85-year-old former shop assistant is asked to read a telephone number and then dial the number without looking at it. What type of memory is being tested here?","options":{"A":"Episodic memory","B":"Iconic memory","C":"Haptic memory","D":"Recognition memory","E":"Semantic memory"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Iconic memory is the memory of visual stimuli. It is part of the visual memory system that includes visual short-term memory and long-term memory."},{"number":34,"question":"Betty is then shown a list of words. After a few moments she is shown another list of words and asked to identify words that appear in both lists.","options":{"A":"Episodic memory","B":"Iconic memory","C":"Haptic memory","D":"Recognition memory","E":"Semantic memory"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Recognition memory is the ability to recognize previously encountered events, objects, or people."},{"number":35,"question":"At your CAMHS inpatient unit, you observe Paolo, a four-year-old boy playing with his dinosaur toy. He treats it as though it is a living object. According to Piaget's model, which stage of cognitive development is he in?","options":{"A":"Sensorimotor","B":"Concrete Operational","C":"Pre-operational","D":"Post-operational","E":"Formal operational"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"This child is displaying animism, which is the belief that plants, inanimate objects, and natural phenomena possess a living soul and have human feelings and intentions. The preoperational stage ranges from about ages 2 to 7."},{"number":36,"question":"Pauline is a first-time mother to Stephanie, her 18-month-old daughter. She is worried that Stephanie isn't talking as well as the other children at the nursery. If an 18-month-old child has normal development, how many words should he or she know at this stage?","options":{"A":"0-10","B":"11-25","C":"25-50","D":"50-85","E":"85-125"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"In normal child development, an 18-month-old child's vocabulary will usually contain 20-50 words."},{"number":37,"question":"Which of the following is an example of an ideology that emphasizes the rights of groups over the individual?","options":{"A":"Socialism","B":"Democracy","C":"Communism","D":"Individualism","E":"Collectivism"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Group rights, also known as collective rights, are rights held by a group rather than by its individual members, the latter of which is termed individualism."},{"number":38,"question":"During Fresher's Week, Kaley, a 20-year-old law student, with no prior psychiatric history, presents to Accident and Emergency with delirium, labile blood pressure, dry mouth and dilated pupils. Which of the following could explain her presentation?","options":{"A":"Anti-muscarinic psychosis","B":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","C":"Serotonin Syndrome","D":"Paracetamol overdose","E":"Cocaine intoxication"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Cocaine is a stimulant made from an alkaloid contained in the leaves of the coca bush. The patient in question is presenting with typical symptoms of cocaine intoxication."},{"number":39,"question":"James comes to your memory clinic with a two-month history of short-term memory loss. He is concerned that he has Parkinson's disease as his late father had suffered from the disease. Which of the following genes is associated with Parkinson's disease?","options":{"A":"Dysbindin","B":"Neuregulin","C":"Alpha synuclein","D":"Presenilin-2","E":"Amyloid Precursor Protein"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Mutations in the following genes; alpha-synuclein (SNCA), parkin (PRKN), leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2), PTEN-induced putative kinase 1 (PINK1) are known to cause Parkinson's disease."},{"number":40,"question":"Toby is a 12-year-old boy in his first year of secondary school. His form tutor complains that he is extremely disruptive in school; jumping on desks and pushing in the cafeteria queue. You have reviewed him in your outpatient clinic and believe him to be suffering from ADHD. You arrange a meeting with his parents to discuss commencing medications. What is the mechanism of action of methylphenidate in treating ADHD?","options":{"A":"Catecholamine re-uptake inhibition","B":"Serotonin re-uptake inhibition","C":"Dopamine agonist","D":"Norepinephrine-Dopamine reuptake inhibitor","E":"Sigma-1 antagonist"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Methylphenidate is a phenethylamine stimulant that binds and blocks norepinephrine and dopamine transporters. It increases the firing rate of norepinephrine and dopamine, which enhances executive functioning."},{"number":41,"question":"Casper Williams is a 25-year-old postgraduate student studying business administration. He attends the student mental health service complaining of memory loss, which is affecting his ability to study. He worries that he will fail his MBA. On exploration of his social history, he admits to frequently using angel dust. Phencyclidine-induced amnesia is due to action on which of the following receptors?","options":{"A":"Serotonin","B":"Acetyl choline","C":"Noradrenaline","D":"Dopamine","E":"Glutamate"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Phencyclidine (PCP, angel dust) primarily acts as an antagonist at ionotropic glutamate receptors such as NMDA."},{"number":42,"question":"Tom has severe anxiety disorder and recently started on Pregabalin. His partner, who is a chemistry graduate, is keen about its receptor action. Pregabalin acts on which of the following receptors?","options":{"A":"Glutamate","B":"Serotonin","C":"Acetyl choline","D":"Noradrenaline","E":"GABA"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Pregabalin is a GABA analogue structurally (similar to gabapentin). It binds to the α2δ subunit of the voltage-dependent calcium channel in the central nervous system and has anti-epileptic, analgesic (neuropathic pain) and anxiolytic effects."},{"number":43,"question":"Hyder is a 35-year-old male on your assessment ward. He has a longstanding history of depression for which he takes citalopram. He complains of pain in his leg having slipped and fallen over on the ward the previous morning. He comes to you asking for painkillers. Which of the following increases GI bleeds with SSRIs?","options":{"A":"Paracetamol","B":"Diclofenac","C":"Tramadol","D":"Ibuprofen gel","E":"Codeine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"SSRIs inhibit the serotonin transporter, which is responsible for the uptake of serotonin into platelets. It is thought that SSRIs deplete platelet serotonin, leading to a reduced ability to form clots and a subsequent increase in the risk of bleeding."},{"number":44,"question":"Mohammed is a 7-year-old boy. His mother told him that he could play outside once he had finished his homework. This is based on which of the following psychological mechanisms?","options":{"A":"Reciprocal inhibition","B":"Classical conditioning","C":"Cognitive mapping","D":"Operant conditioning","E":"Premack's principle"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"This is Premack's principle, which states that high frequency behaviour can be used to reinforce low-frequency behaviour."},{"number":45,"question":"Empathy skills are most likely to be delayed in which of the following?","options":{"A":"A deaf child of deaf parents","B":"A deaf child of hearing parents","C":"A hearing child of deaf parents","D":"A hearing child of hearing parents","E":"A hearing child with one deaf parent"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Deaf children with deaf parents have access to communication between signing adults. Deaf children brought up by hearing parents are at a disadvantage as there is less signing in this group."},{"number":46,"question":"Which of the following is seen in a normal child development?","options":{"A":"Babbling with consonant sounds at 7 months","B":"Social smile at 6 months","C":"Toilet training at 5 years","D":"Putting two words together at 4 years","E":"Beginning to crawl at 15 months"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Babbling is the production of articulate sounds that are not yet recognizable words. It begins shortly after birth, and at around 7 months, babbling contains alternations of vowels and consonants."},{"number":47,"question":"Which of the following is NOT a risk factor for delayed speech development?","options":{"A":"Absence of a father","B":"Rapid successive pregnancies","C":"Small family size","D":"Low levels of parental education","E":"Smoking in pregnancy"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The important family risk factors associated with delayed language development in children include large family size, smoking in pregnancy, rapid successive pregnancies, absence of father, low levels of parental education, divorce, marital disharmony & violence."},{"number":48,"question":"In the WAIS-R test battery for intelligence, which sub-test is resistant to brain damage/injury?","options":{"A":"Digital span","B":"Digit symbol","C":"Similarities","D":"Block design","E":"Picture completion"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Tests on WAIS are either 'hold' or 'no hold'. The so-called 'hold tests' in WAIS are thought to reflect the use of old knowledge and are relatively resistant to the effects of brain damage and aging."},{"number":49,"question":"Which of the following has the strongest correlation with developmental language delay?","options":{"A":"Maternal smoking during pregnancy","B":"Maternal alcohol use during pregnancy","C":"Low socio-economic status of mother","D":"High fibre diet","E":"Immigration"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Smoking during pregnancy and large family size are the strongest risk factors for developmental language delay."},{"number":50,"question":"Clive is a 27-year-old skateboard artist with paranoid schizophrenia. He was commenced on clozapine two months ago. He attends his GP complaining of severe chest pain. His GP takes recordings of his vitals and performs an ECG. What is likely to be seen on Clive's ECG?","options":{"A":"ST depression","B":"ST elevation","C":"Prolonged QT","D":"Tall peaked u waves","E":"Pathological q waves"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Clive is most likely suffering from myocarditis, an inflammation of the heart that can be caused by clozapine. ECG findings include diffuse T wave inversions and saddle-shaped ST segment elevations."},{"number":51,"question":"According to the DSM-5, which of the following is true regarding changes to the diagnostic criteria of psychotic illnesses?","options":{"A":"All subtypes of schizophrenia were removed","B":"Simple schizophrenia is not a formal diagnosis","C":"Schizotypal disorder is now classified amongst schizophrenia","D":"Schizophreniform illness is no longer classified amongst schizophrenia","E":"Catatonia is strongly associated with schizophrenia."},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The DSM-5 is the 2013 update to the American Psychiatric Association's (APA) classification and diagnostic tool. Changes were made in the diagnostic criteria and coding of Schizophrenia spectrum and other psychotic disorders, including the removal of all subtypes of schizophrenia."},{"number":52,"question":"According to the World Health Organization, which of the following constitutes the strongest risk factor for domestic violence?","options":{"A":"Being female","B":"Partner misuses substances","C":"Social deprivation","D":"Low social economic status","E":"Low education"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The key risk factor for being a victim of all forms of domestic and gender-based violence is being female."},{"number":53,"question":"A psychology student is keen to know about the ICD-10 duration criteria for the diagnosis of Mania. The episode should last at least;","options":{"A":"1 day","B":"2 days","C":"1 week","D":"2 weeks","E":"4 weeks"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Both ICD-10 and DSM-4 specify that the manic episode should last at least 1 week and the disturbance is sufficiently severe enough to impair social and occupational functioning."},{"number":54,"question":"The Nerve Supply of Superior Oblique muscle is;","options":{"A":"Oculomotor","B":"Trochlear","C":"Trigeminal","D":"Facial","E":"Abducent"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The Superior oblique is the only extra ocular muscle innervated by the trochlear nerve."},{"number":55,"question":"Sophie had a review in the outpatients' clinic for her depressive disorder. The Psychiatrist is keen to start her on Agomelatine. Which of the following baseline investigations should be done before starting her on this drug?","options":{"A":"Complete blood count","B":"Liver function test","C":"Kidney function test","D":"Thyroid function test","E":"ECG"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Liver toxicity is a side effect of Agomelatine. Liver function tests should be performed in every patient before starting him or her on this drug. LFTs should be monitored at 3, 6, 12, and 24 weeks after starting treatment."},{"number":56,"question":"Which of the following drugs may exacerbate the symptoms of Schizophrenia due to NMDA receptor antagonistic activity?","options":{"A":"Cannabis","B":"Cocaine","C":"Amphetamine","D":"Ketamine","E":"LSD"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"NMDA receptor antagonists like Ketamine and Phencyclidine have been shown to induce both positive and negative symptoms of Schizophrenia in healthy volunteers."},{"number":57,"question":"Which of the following is the biggest risk factor for developing NMS?","options":{"A":"Older age","B":"Female gender","C":"Starting on anticholinergic medications","D":"Afrocarribbean ethnicity","E":"Sudden withdrawal of antiparkinsonian medication"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The syndrome of NMS has been described in all age groups. Age is not a risk factor. Men outnumber women 2 fold. Sudden withdrawal of antiparkinsonian medication is one of the high-risk factors for developing NMS."},{"number":58,"question":"Which of the following structures is involved in the pathophysiology of Wernicke's encephalopathy?","options":{"A":"Hippocampus","B":"Prefrontal cortex","C":"Amygdala","D":"Basal ganglia","E":"Mamillary bodies"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"In Wernicke's encephalopathy, pathological lesions are seen in mammillary bodies, thalamic nuclei and the walls of the third ventricle."},{"number":59,"question":"A grandmother says to her grandchild, 'You must eat your greens before you go to play outside'. Which psychological mechanism is used here?","options":{"A":"Premack's principle","B":"Reciprocal inhibition","C":"Counterconditioning","D":"Overt sensitization","E":"Classical conditioning"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Premack's principle is also called the relative theory of reinforcement, often used with young children. It states that more probable behaviour (like play outside) will reinforce less probable behavior (like eating greens)."},{"number":60,"question":"'Saw tooth wave pattern' in EEG is seen in which of the following phases of sleep?","options":{"A":"Stage 1 n-REM sleep","B":"Stage 2 n-REM sleep","C":"Stage 3 n-REM sleep","D":"Stage 4 n-REM sleep","E":"REM sleep"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The sawtooth wave is a distinctive pattern in electroencephalogram (EEG) that occurs only in REM sleep and that is recorded mainly in the central scalp area."},{"number":61,"question":"Which of the following antipsychotic is a highly selective dopamine antagonist?","options":{"A":"Chlorpromazine","B":"Haloperidol","C":"Olanzapine","D":"Clozapine","E":"Sulpride"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Amisulpride and Sulpride have highly selective dopamine antagonistic property."},{"number":62,"question":"Benzodiazepines enhance the effects of which of the following neurotransmitters?","options":{"A":"Dopamine","B":"Serotonin","C":"GABA","D":"Acetyl choline","E":"Norepinephrine"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"It is widely believed that benzodiazepines enhance the effects of the neurotransmitter gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA). They do so through action at benzodiazepine receptors."},{"number":63,"question":"Which class of drugs should be avoided in organic disinhibition?","options":{"A":"Sodium valproate","B":"Olanzapine","C":"Benzodiazepines","D":"SSRIs","E":"Trazadone"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Benzodiazepines should be avoided in organic disinhibition. There is some evidence that SSRIs and Trazadone may ameliorate disinhibition in fronto-temporal dementia."},{"number":64,"question":"Which of the following deletion syndromes is considered as the highest known genetic risk factor for schizophrenia other than having a monozygotic twin sibling with the illness?","options":{"A":"5q 11.2","B":"14 q 11.2","C":"19 q 11.2","D":"22 q 11.2","E":"25 q 11.2"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"People with 22q11.2 deletion syndrome (velo-cardio-facial syndrome) have a 30-fold risk of developing schizophrenia. During adolescence and early adulthood, up to 30% of people with the syndrome develop schizophrenia."},{"number":65,"question":"An ECG should be carried out on presentation in a patient with anorexia nervosa if BMI is less than;","options":{"A":"16","B":"19","C":"20","D":"22","E":"25"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"In patients with anorexia, a screening assessment of risk should include a minimum of blood pressure, pulse, BMI, temperature, and tests of proximal myopathy. An ECG should be carried out if weight is low (BMI <16)."},{"number":66,"question":"Which of the following conditions is associated with polycystic ovarian syndrome?","options":{"A":"Anorexia nervosa","B":"Bulimia nervosa","C":"Body dysmorphic disorder","D":"Binge eating disorder","E":"Muscle dysmorphia"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Absent follicular development is seen in 20% of women with bulimia and bulimia is associated with polycystic ovarian syndrome."},{"number":67,"question":"The strongest treatable risk factor for vascular dementia is;","options":{"A":"Diabetes","B":"Hypertension","C":"Hypercholesterolemia","D":"Atrial fibrillation","E":"Obesity"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The Syst-Eur and PROGRESS studies showed small but significant reductions in dementia from treating hypertension. Hypertension is now considered the strongest treatable risk factor for vascular dementia."},{"number":68,"question":"What is the most common psychiatric diagnosis among those presenting to emergency departments following self-harm?","options":{"A":"Schizophrenia","B":"Depression","C":"Panic disorder","D":"Adjustment disorder","E":"Post traumatic stress disorder"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The most common psychiatric diagnosis among those presenting to emergency departments following self-harm is Adjustment disorder."},{"number":69,"question":"The gene most strongly implicated in ADHD is","options":{"A":"Dopamine 1 receptor gene","B":"Dopamine 2 receptor gene","C":"Dopamine 3 receptor gene","D":"Dopamine 4 receptor gene","E":"Dopamine 5 receptor gene"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The gene most strongly implicated in ADHD is the D dopamine receptor gene DRD4."},{"number":70,"question":"CADASIL is associated with mutation in which of the following genes?","options":{"A":"Parkin gene","B":"Notch3","C":"COMT","D":"LRRK2","E":"Dysbindin"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"An unusual form of subcortical small vessel disease occurs in the rare inherited condition of CADASIL (cerebral autosomal dominant arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy) in which a mutation in the Notch3 gene results in deposition of granular material in the walls of small arteries and arterioles."},{"number":71,"question":"The symptoms of adjustment disorder resolve within;","options":{"A":"1 week of termination of the stressor","B":"2 weeks of termination of the stressor","C":"1 month of termination of the stressor","D":"3 months of termination of the stressor","E":"6 months of termination of the stressor"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Adjustment disorder requires a stressor and that the symptoms should resolve within 6 months of termination of the stressor or its consequences."},{"number":72,"question":"Which one among the following is an environmental factor associated with ADHD?","options":{"A":"Food and additive allergies","B":"Low-protein","C":"High-carbohydrate diets","D":"Prematurity","E":"Essential fatty acid deficiencies"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The environmental risk factors associated with ADHD include Prenatal and/or perinatal risks (e.g., prematurity, low birth weight, exposure to toxins), among other factors."},{"number":73,"question":"Mutations in the progranulin gene are known to cause;","options":{"A":"Creutzfeldt Jakob disease","B":"CADASIL","C":"Parkinson's disease","D":"Lewy body dementia","E":"Frontotemporal dementia"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Mutations in the progranulin gene are known to cause frontotemporal lobar degeneration, leading to dementia."},{"number":74,"question":"A child attains gender identity in which stage of Freud's psychosexual development?","options":{"A":"Oral phase","B":"Anal phase","C":"Phallic phase","D":"Latent phase","E":"Genital phase"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"In the Phallic phase (between the ages of 3-7), the child learns to realize the differences between males and females and becomes aware of its own sexuality."},{"number":75,"question":"The preferential attachment of a baby to one adult female figure is called;","options":{"A":"Secure attachment pattern","B":"Proximity seeking","C":"Monotropy","D":"Universal attachment","E":"Separation distress"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Monotropy is the view that the child initially forms attachment to one caregiver, usually the mother. It describes the child's tendency to prefer the primary caregiver."},{"number":76,"question":"'Driving a car' is an example of what type of memory?","options":{"A":"Declarative","B":"Semantic","C":"Episodic","D":"Working","E":"Long term memory"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Driving a car is an example of procedural memory, which is classified under non-declarative memory. Non-declarative memory is a component of long-term memory."},{"number":77,"question":"According to Kohlberg, which one among the following represent Conventional Stage?","options":{"A":"Social Contract","B":"Authority","C":"Universal Ethics","D":"Obedience","E":"Punishment"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Social order or Authority Orientation represents conventional stage in Kohlberg's theory of moral development. The person upholds law and social rules to avoid the censure of the authorities and feelings of guilt about not doing one's duty."},{"number":78,"question":"You are asked to see a patient in the medical ward. He was clinically depressed and treated on Fluoxetine. His routine investigations showed sodium levels of 122 mol/L. Fluoxetine has now been stopped. Which of the following anti-depressants would be a suitable option in this situation?","options":{"A":"Mirtazapine","B":"Citalopram","C":"Paroxetine","D":"Amitriptyline","E":"Moclobemide"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"This person has developed hyponatraemia following treatment with antidepressants such as Fluoxetine. For those who develop hyponatraemia with an SSRI, consider Noradrenergic drugs such as Nortriptyline and Lofepramine or an MAOI such as Moclobemide."},{"number":79,"question":"What type of EEG changes are routinely seen in Delirium Tremens?","options":{"A":"Low voltage fast activity","B":"Diffuse slowing of the background rhythm","C":"Increased triphasic waves","D":"Generalized periodic 1-2 Hz sharp waves","E":"Focal delta activity."},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Electroencephalography (EEG) can be useful in differentiating delirium from other conditions. The EEG shows a diffuse slowing of the background rhythm, in patients with delirium. In patients with delirium tremens, the EEG shows low voltage fast activity superimposed on slow waves."},{"number":80,"question":"A teacher rewarded Jimmy with a star sticker for his good behaviour. It represents which type of learning?","options":{"A":"Classical conditioning","B":"Operant conditioning","C":"Social learning","D":"Aversive learning","E":"Cognitive learning"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Rewarding a child with star stickers for good behaviour is an example of positive reinforcement. It is said to take place when the behaviour is maintained or increased by producing consequences that the person finds rewarding. This is one of the principles used in operant conditioning."},{"number":81,"question":"A psychologist is involved in treating a patient with fear of heights. He requested the patient to imagine standing on top of the building without actual real exposure to them. The psychological principle employed here is;","options":{"A":"Reciprocal inhibition","B":"Aversion","C":"Flooding","D":"Implosion","E":"Punishment"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Flooding is an operant conditioning technique where actual exposure to feared stimulus takes place for a substantial amount of time so the accompanying anxiety response fades away while the stimulus is continuously present. When a similar technique is attempted with imagined not actual exposure then it is called as implosion."},{"number":82,"question":"Tom has a history of severe alcohol dependence. He has been given Disulfiram to reduce the frequency of drinking alcohol. This is an example of;","options":{"A":"Premack's principle","B":"Avoidance learning","C":"Aversive conditioning","D":"Covert reinforcement","E":"Covert sensitization"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Aversive conditioning: This is an operant conditioning where punishment is used to reduce the frequency of target behaviour e.g. the use of Disulfiram (noxious stimuli) to reduce the frequency of drinking alcohol."},{"number":83,"question":"Which among the following EEG waves and their frequency is incorrectly matched?","options":{"A":"Alpha waves- 8 to 13 Hz","B":"Beta waves- more than 13 Hz","C":"Theta waves- 7-11 Hz","D":"Delta waves- < 4 Hz","E":"Lambda- single waves"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The frequency of Theta waves is 4 to 8 Hz. Mu waves occur over the motor cortex and their frequency is between 7-11 Hz."},{"number":84,"question":"Which of the following can be used as an adjuvant to Risperidone to reduce Hyperprolactinaemia?","options":{"A":"Sulpiride","B":"Amisulpride","C":"Trazadone","D":"Naloxone","E":"Aripiprazole"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Hyperprolactinaemia and related symptoms are reported to improve fairly promptly following the addition of non-prolactin elevating drug such as Aripiprazole."},{"number":85,"question":"Which drug should be used with caution in patients with psoriasis?","options":{"A":"Haloperidol","B":"Lithium","C":"Carbamazepine","D":"Sodium valproate","E":"Olanzapine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Lithium is involved in a variety of cutaneous reactions including psoriasis, which may present as exacerbation of preexisting psoriasis, induction of de novo psoriasis, pustular psoriasis, nail changes, and psoriatic arthropathy."},{"number":86,"question":"Lucy is taking antipsychotic medications and complained of sexual dysfunction, menstrual disturbances and galactorrhoea. Which dopamine pathway when affected by antipsychotic drugs can induce such symptoms?","options":{"A":"Mesocortical pathway","B":"Mesolimbic pathway","C":"Niagrostriatal pathway","D":"Tuberoinfundibular pathway","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Lucy is exhibiting features of raised prolactin levels. Hyperprolactinaemia is associated with a number of adverse consequences such as sexual dysfunction, menstrual disturbances, breast growth, galactorrhoea and reductions in bone mineral density."},{"number":87,"question":"Huntington's disease is a progressive neurodegenerative disorder, which is characterized by;","options":{"A":"CCA > 35 expansion","B":"CCA < 35 expansion","C":"CTG > 35 expansion","D":"CAG > 35 expansion","E":"CAG < 35 expansion"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Huntington's disease (HD) is a progressive neurodegenerative disorder with autosomal-dominant inheritance. The disease is caused by a CAG trinucleotide repeat expansion located in the first exon of the HD gene."},{"number":88,"question":"Paul has been diagnosed with frontotemporal dementia. He has a strong family history. A mutation on which of the following chromosome predisposes a person to develop this condition?","options":{"A":"5","B":"7","C":"17","D":"19","E":"22"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) refers to the three different syndromes of frontotemporal dementia (FTD), progressive non-fluent aphasia and semantic dementia. In familial cases, mutations have been identified in the microtubule-associated protein tau gene (MAPT) on chromosome 17q21."},{"number":89,"question":"A 26-year-old woman on psychotropic medications presents to the A&E department in a confused state. On examination, she has fever, raised BP, excessive sweating and bilateral clonus. The most likely diagnosis is;","options":{"A":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","B":"Serotonin syndrome","C":"Antidepressant discontinuation syndrome","D":"Hyponatraemia","E":"Munchausen syndrome"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Serotonin syndrome is a rare but potentially fatal syndrome occurring in the context of initiation or dose increase of a serotonergic agent, characterized by altered mental state, agitation, tremor, shivering, diarrhea, hyperreflexia, clonus, ataxia and hyperthermia."},{"number":90,"question":"Rosy has been diagnosed with generalized anxiety disorder. Which drug is licensed in the treatment of GAD?","options":{"A":"Gabapentin","B":"Topiramate","C":"Lamotrigine","D":"Pregabalin","E":"Aripiprazole"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Pregabalin is licensed in the treatment of GAD. Several large RCTs have demonstrated its efficacy and tolerability and comparable speed of onset of action to a benzodiazepine."},{"number":91,"question":"A 33-year-old woman is taking paroxetine for a few months. She developed pins & needles and shock-like sensations in her legs. The diagnosis is;","options":{"A":"Serotonin syndrome","B":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","C":"Antidepressant discontinuation syndrome","D":"Akathisia","E":"Dyskinesia"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Antidepressant discontinuation symptoms include irritability, nausea, ataxia, diaphoresis, paresthesia and increased dreaming. The onset of symptoms is usually within 5 days of stopping treatment and depends on the half-life of the antidepressant."},{"number":92,"question":"Phencyclidine acts on which receptor to produce symptoms of schizophrenia?","options":{"A":"AMPA","B":"Kainate","C":"NMDA receptor","D":"Dopamine receptor","E":"Serotonin receptor"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Phencyclidine blocks the activity of the NMDA receptor. It is an NMDA receptor antagonist that induces both positive and negative symptoms of Schizophrenia in healthy volunteers."},{"number":93,"question":"John has depressive disorder. He is skeptical about taking antidepressants as he had sexual side effects with them. Which of the following has the lowest risk of sexual dysfunction?","options":{"A":"Sertraline","B":"Mirtazapine","C":"Venlafaxine","D":"Agomelatine","E":"Trazadone"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"With Agomelatine, there is no clear effect on orgasm, erection or libido. The incidence of sexual dysfunction is similar to placebo."}]`);export{e as default};
